talk and I think there's also a paper
behind it of this idea that uh one
sizefits all database systems not
optimal one size actually fits none and
that what you really want is database
solutions that target specific needs
what database offerings you see today
that are one-sizefits-all in 2004 when I
wrote the paper we had an academic
project which was building what became
streambase
And so a stream processing engine looks
nothing like a relational database.
And we had the gist of an idea for
column stores for the for data
warehouses which was popularized by
Vertica looks nothing like a row store.
So here were three wildly different
implementations that had no resemblance
to each other and in each case they were
an order of magnitude faster than the
other guys. So it's pretty clear that
one side, you know, that in with those
three instances,
you give up an order of magnitude
uh when you're running a database system
that isn't
that isn't architected for your kind of
stuff. I think that's still true. I
mean, I think Clickhouse is a column
store. Pine cone is faster than
userdefined types
on on textbased vector processing.
And so I think it's it's still very much
the case [snorts] and I think
there's no difficulty
putting a common parser on top of
multiple implementations.
uh Postgress has so far chosen not to do
that. they don't implement a column
store
and so I think they are not they are not
competitive you know on sizable data
warehouses
they also don't have multi-node support
again for people with big data
warehouses that's table stakes so I
think it's just as true today as it ever
was I think that
what is true
is that if you want to get going, you
have a database problem,
you know, the answer is choose Postgress
[snorts] and there's a huge programming
community, all kinds of all kinds of,
you know, data type implementations.
it's free uh and you can find Postgress
talent easily and get going
and and so I think it's it's it's a
great choice for lowest common
denominator
and until you're trying to do [snorts] a
million transactions a second it works
just fine until you're trying to support
a pedibyte data warehouse it it I say at
the low end it it's absolutely
Absolutely the right one sizefits all at
the low end it's postgress at the high
end that's just not true
>> GPUs do they make available some new
opportunities to optimize databases
probably but I think the the big
challenge is that GPUs are
you know sumd sim you know single
instruction multi- data and that's
that's the anathema of indexing
And so whenever indexing is the right
answer,
they're probably not a good idea.
And I think uh also you've got to
architect them so that the so that the
bandwidth
so that the bandwidth from storage is is
not not the bottleneck. And so if
they're an add-on to the CPU as often as
not the bus connecting it to the the GPU
to the CPU is a bottleneck.
>> Can you explain why indexing would be
not as effective when there's SIMD?
>> So let's let's say I'm I'm [snorts]
looking for Ryan's
I'm looking for Ryan's salary and I have
a B tree.
So you go to the root of the B tree.
You find you find the divider that has
both sides of Ryan.
You follow the pointer.
That's a memory access for sure. Then
you do it all again and you do this like
three or four times.
So that doesn't parallelize well. So the
answer is indexing doesn't parallelize
well. You mentioned B trees. When you
first implemented
uh that first version of ingress, did
you write all of that by hand? Because I
imagine there's probably not some
existing B tree library or something.
>> Yeah, we wrote the original version of
ingress was all written from scratch.
>> What was the hardest part of that
implementation?
>> Uh query optimizer.
>> And why was that hard?
>> It's tough. It's it's just
algorithmically difficult.